welcome to Cheyenne Regional Medical
Center cardiac rehab heart education
class during the video please feel free
to write down any questions you may have
after viewing the video you may call our
number listed on the screen monday
through friday 9 a.m. to 3 p.m. to talk
to one of our cardiac rehab team to ask
questions or obtain more information and
once again we'll have our phone number
also posted at the end of the video in
case you did not get the information
here in the front heart education
knowledge is power
in this presentation we will cover the
different types of heart disease risk
factors associated with heart disease
tests and interventions emotional
well-being medications that are often
prescribed with heart disease and then
symptoms of heart attack heart failure
stroke and pa D so let's start with the
types of heart disease first there is
coronary artery disease this is when the
vessels in and around the heart become
blocked or hardened and this decreases
the blood flow to that muscle to feed it
valvular disease this is when your
valves inside the heart become leaky or
stiff and do not function like they're
supposed to we have heart failure this
is when damaged or weakened heart muscle
occurs and this can do happen due to
heart attack issues with your valves
rhythm disorders or other things that
are going on finally we have rhythm
disorders such as atrial fibrillation or
the top part of the heart beats
uncontrollably and the bottom beats
normally this is a problem where then we
don't have proper blood flow through the
heart and the muscle can get more tired
and stressed we also have the Fast and
Slow arrhythmias next up is risk factors
for heart disease they fall into two
different categories we have modifiable
and non-modifiable in the modifiable
category these are things that we can do
or things that we have going on that we
can fix by changing our lifestyle habits
they include high blood pressure or
hypertension we can modify this by
watching what we eat by reducing our
sodium by taking our medications
prescribed by exercise high cholesterol
we can also fix this through diet
exercise our diet here in America we
have turned to a lot of processed foods
quick meals and things like that and we
really need to switch back to fresh
fruits and vegetables cooking our own
foods and flavoring them with spices
other than just salt stress stress is a
huge risk factor and a lot of us do not
realize how much stress we have going on
in our lives being inactive not taking
the time to get out to walk to exercise
is something that we need to modify
being overweight excess alcohol use
smoking and tobacco products and then
diabetes is listed on the bottom you
notice that one is in red and that's
because it falls in both categories
diabetes is something that we are
diagnosed with and will have to deal
with for the rest of our lives but it
can be modifiable we can watch what we
can eat we can reduce our salt our sugar
intake we can take our medications as
prescribed we can do things to control
the diabetes so our risk factors go down
with that the non-modifiable risk
factors are things that we have no
control over such as hereditary and
genetics what we get from Grandma and
Grandpa mom and dad that is who we are
we cannot change that age as we travel
around the Sun year after year we grow
older our bodies have more issues going
on with it gender plays a huge role in
this all so whether you're male or
female men typically have are diagnosed
with heart disease earlier in life than
women women are diagnosed more so
towards our 60s and 70s with heart
disease
and then diabetes also once again fall
in this category stress and emotional
health it is a big deal
chronic stress can lead to heart disease
when we are under stress our body
excretes more cortisone that's a hormone
in our body that we naturally gives out
when stress levels are up in order to
combat stress when we raise our cortisol
levels due to chronic stress we have
increased chance for atherosclerosis
which is hardening of the arteries
it increases our overall cholesterol in
our body and it increases our blood
sugar all these things together play in
a risk of having heart disease our
vessels do not respond well to increase
cholesterol increase blood sugar and
hardening of the vessels types of
stressors they can be good and bad
stressors what I like to present here is
something good and beautiful a lot of us
see new form babies as just these lovely
wonderful things new life new beginnings
they snuggle in a squirm a little it's
just a wonderful feeling
Grandma and Grandpa aunts and uncles
love newborns brand new moms and dads on
the other hand they're in love with this
new child but after everyone leaves and
the child isn't sleeping isn't eating as
crying a lot is being too changed a lot
it's a lot of new stressors that a new
mom and dad are not ready for always
despite all the good that comes with a
child they have a different sense of
stress with this also what am I doing
wrong why are they crying all the time
why don't they sleep what am I doing
wrong um so you can see it one beautiful
thing can be a good stressor and a bad
stressor depending upon how you react to
it strong emotions are you one of those
that are always angry and what I like to
use here is that driver heading down to
one of the big cities if you're driving
and you get white knuckles and you're
that angry driver and and just yelling
at all the other car
are you just one that says huh I gave
myself an extra hour because I expect
this was gonna happen I'm just gonna
listen to my news music and kind of kick
back and go with the flow untreated
depression or anxiety is another
stressor we don't always see this as a
common stressor or what we think of this
stress but if you are having depression
that is putting your body through stress
if you have high anxieties that is
putting your body through stress please
follow up with a physician get in
counseling if you need it
make sure you are taking care of
yourself
ways to invest in your emotional health
remember to keep a strong support group
system around you whether that be one or
two people or ten or fifteen everyone's
gonna be different as to how many people
they feel they need to have around them
keep the line of communication open
letting people know how you were doing
even if you just need to vent and you
don't need someone to respond to it you
just need to get it off your chest
join a community organization give back
volunteering is a wonderful thing there
are studies out there that says
voluntary just a minimum of three hours
a month gives you back the feelings of
giving back to those in need or those
that are in want it gives you a lot of
endorphins makes you feel better makes
you more calm and relaxed remember to
take time for yourself and excuse
yourself from other people's problems
this is definitely more difficult I
think for women than men cuz women are
more geared towards nurturing and trying
to make things right but it is okay to
say no I cannot do that and if you're
one of those personalities but you are
more stressed out by saying no come up
with a plan say no I cannot do it this
week I am too busy I need time for
myself but next Tuesday I can help you
or something that way you're taking some
of that stress if you say no but you're
also taking that time for yourself and
looking at what will work for you and
not necess
really only for the other person learn
to build some coping mechanisms are you
one of those that react a response back
to that driver in the big city the white
knuckles the passing the cutting people
off or even lay back one that will just
listen to your music and go with the
flow make yourself a plan when you feel
a certain way I'm gonna do ABC when my
children were a lot younger there is
times that I just needed a low time
maybe not the best thing to do but I put
them in front of the TV put their
favorite TV show on going in the
bathroom turn on all the water and stuff
so I just couldn't hear what's going on
for three four or five minutes so I
could take some deep breaths relax and
be ready to go back to taking care of
them and being the support person that I
needed to be for them talking to a
professional a counselor a psychiatrist
anyone that has some training that can
help you
insurance companies are more than
willing to pay for this because mental
health is a huge thing we're realizing
in the last ten years that mental health
is a huge part of the whole body a lot
of insurance companies if you call them
up they will have programs out there
that they will say yes if you go to one
of these ten people will pay a hundred
percent of your visits for X number of
visits so please reach out to your
insurance company see what their it
there is to offer you because a lot of
people are uncomfortable one talking to
a counselor because it's going to cost
too much money
or to the idea of talking to someone
else we're a very closed society it's
alright to reach out talk to people
sometimes it's easier to talk to a
stranger because you don't feel like
there's gonna be judgment there learn to
develop some relaxation techniques try
something new go back to something old
both things are great the reading the
walking The Hiding
hiking meditation meditation is just
some deep breathing
in deeply hold it a little bit let it
all out
let your mind just go blank for a little
bit it really helps in lowering blood
pressure lowering stress levels makes
you feel good a lot of people like to do
busy stuff with their hands other people
decompress in front of the TV for a
little bit do what works for you find
something new so that you can try when
something old is not working anymore
next one is goals
oles is a huge thing throughout our
entire lives as we get older and we get
to retirement age we don't necessarily
think of goals anymore because we felt
like we achieved them throughout our
lives when we were younger and having
goals - what job we want how many
children we want what sort of person
we're looking for in a spouse things
like that we achieve those goals and we
mark them off on a list but that list
should never go away you should continue
to add to it the importance of health
goals go way beyond the heart it goes
way beyond everyday life so creating a
healthy baseline enables you to tolerate
higher levels activity so many of us as
when we get to the retirement age or our
children are still young and we want to
be active with them we need to remember
that we need a healthy baseline so that
we can keep up with the kids keep up
with our grandkids go back to the
mountains when we retire anything that
we found a lot of love in healthy
baseline will help us heal faster from
illness injury anything like that so
even if you are watching this video and
you haven't been diagnosed with heart
disease just remember Zacks healthy
baseline will help you in the future so
setting SMART goals SMART goals is an
acronym it means specific measurable
action orientated or in this place I
like the word adjustable also realistic
time bound these are so important when
you think of making goals for you
whether they're sure
term or long term that you think about
how specific you want it to be the more
specific you are the easier its to
obtain because you know it it means how
its defined making sure is measurable it
allows you to monitor it to chart it in
a way that you know you're reaching that
goal making it adjustable is huge you do
not know if down the road you might fall
and break a hip you might end up finding
a food intolerance that you didn't
realize you had before you might come
down with a flu bug or something that
sets you back for a little bit you need
to be able to adjust these goals make it
realistic know where you are right now
and set goals to get where you want to
be if you're someone who has never owned
a pair of tennis shoes in your life
you're not gonna be able to run a 5k in
the next three months you need to work
up to it maybe your goal will be walk
the 5k in three months run one in a year
things like that make sure it's time
bound someday is not any day of the week
be specific it is so important here that
you do that I have example here up on
the screen a bowl I want to eat better
what does that mean what does that mean
to you be specific when you think of
what eating better means to you it might
be every day I'm gonna make for healthy
swaps with my food replace any beverages
throughout the day with water and cut my
usual portions back by a third a lot of
people like extra help with that if you
can write it out it's easier to remember
it it's easier to refer back to it have
a sticky note up on the mirror coming up
with an incentive that goes with this it
could just be as simple as listing by
doing this I will achieve a lower
cholesterol a lower weight I will have
more energy and start feeling better
about myself
and how I look getting into better shape
is good for my health different things
like that make your incentives also come
up with a reward for yourself here
rewards are great if you achieve your
goal say it's a weight-loss goal I want
to lose 10 pounds in the next 3 months
you achieve that goal what is your
reward for yourself is it gonna be
getting that pair of shoes you didn't
quite want to buy or taking that road
trip to the mountains or wherever just
think about little incentives little
rewards to make it easier to reach those
goals and then another thing to keep in
mind is Windows create a goal that
allows for variability and performance
know that if you had a goal that you
want to be able to walk 30 consecutive
minutes and you realize that 3 months
into it that you're only able to do 2025
minutes because of a bad knee remember
that put a window in there make it be
variable so that it can work for you and
you can still achieve it so instead of
30 consecutive minutes say 20 to 30
minutes and then you'll have that window
and you can work towards it knowing that
you do have a bad knee that flares up in
weather changes also controllable make
sure that you avoid goals that focus on
outcomes that you cannot control for
example you may notice that a friend or
a family member can walk really briskly
on a treadmill or outside but you feel
like you should be a walk that same way
but you're not able to look that maybe
that other person is a little younger
than you
maybe that person doesn't have arthritis
so remember you need to set your goals
for yourself and not based off of you
seeing everyone else here's the next
example of the goal this one's an
exercise one you want to exercise for 30
minutes aerobic
exercise four to six times per week in
order to get to your goal you may be
attending cardiac rehab right now and so
you know you do that on Monday Wednesday
and Friday here in Cheyenne and so on
two or three other days of the week you
will exercise for 30 minutes at 8 a.m.
by walking around the mall or your
neighborhood you're gonna be very
specific write it on your calendar so
you can achieve that goal so here's the
nitty-gritty stuff
tasin interventions what are the first
steps to finding out that you have heart
disease or something's going on
often we start with an EKG that is when
they stick those millions of stickers on
you and we always miss pulling one off
and we get a electrical feedback of how
your heart is beating this electrical
feedback tells us if we noticing
anything that may be abnormal or
irregular next we'll also do bloodwork
often you get several vials drawn it
feels like they're taking all your blood
out of your body
it's a only a few vials we run a few
tests and once those lab work come back
then we have an idea of what's going on
if you are getting this blood work done
through the ER because of chest pain or
something else going on just understand
that you will be there for several hours
because they are going to do repeat
blood work to check to see if there is
any changes going on what we're looking
at specifically is your troponin levels
it's an enzyme that the heart leaks out
in times of injury it's specific to the
heart muscle only we also look at CK CK
and B and those are things that are
leaked out from all muscles throughout
the body right now it is taking
approximately six hours in order for
your body to build up those levels
enough for our current test to pick them
up so you'll get a blood draw when you
arrive initially in the ER and then
again approximately six hours later this
timeframe is constantly decreasing as
our testing equipment and ability gets
better
better with knowledge and scientific
research we're hoping that this this
timeframe will go down to three hours
and maybe even less over time next up is
the stress test they're often done on
the treadmill where you walk at a brisk
pace with varying elevations in the
treadmill we monitor your heart rate
your blood pressure your EKG making sure
everything is going okay stress tests
can also be performed with medications
for those that are unable to walk on a
treadmill and where they give you
medications that speed up your heart
rate to mimic actual exercise next we
have the echocardiogram or the echo if
you look at the heart in the center of
the screen you will notice that it is
beating this is a normally beating heart
you notice that the top part of the
heart squeezes and then the bottom part
of the heart squeezes together and
that's for the four chambers of the
heart
the top part has two chambers squeezes
blood down to the bottom two chambers
and then the bottom two chambers squeeze
the blood outside of the heart the left
ventricle is the workhorse of the heart
this is a very important side of the
heart it is the part of the heart that
we do look at what your ejection
fraction is and I will go over to that
in a little bit so when we do an
echocardiogram we're looking at the
condition of the heart muscle is it
beating evenly is all parts of the heart
moving in uniform we look at the valves
are they opening and closing properly is
there blood regurgitating through them
that's not getting pumped all the way
out we are looking for blood cop clots
and the various chambers of the hearts
and then we're looking at that ejection
fraction or the EF it's a measurement of
how well the heart is pumping so in that
left ventricle
it's the workhorse it's where it
squeezes the blood out of the heart
we're looking at how much blood get
squeezed out of that heart with each
beat normally the body squeezes
approximately 60 to 65% of the blood out
of the set
outside of the heart not a hundred
percent as if it squeezed a hundred
percent of blood out of the heart the
heart would collapse on itself and would
not have an easy time reopening and
refilling so once that ejection fraction
begins to fall get less than sixty or
sixty-five percent you are approaching
what we call heart failure so once you
get to forty five percent or less of the
of the blood being pumped out of that
heart you will be diagnosed with heart
failure heart failure is not the end of
the world diagnosis there are things
that we can do to help improve that
heart function that heart pumping action
one of them is medications another one
is diet last one is exercise these are
all things we talk about while you're in
cardiac rehab we work with you on
cardiac rehab but what causes your
ejection fraction to decrease what
causes heart failure it is caused by
damage to the heart muscle when you have
a heart attack part of the heart muscle
can die and therefore it doesn't
function properly anymore if your valves
become leaky or stiff that heart
squeezing motion has issues if you have
uncontrolled afib that can weaken the
heart muscle although next is the left
heart catheterization this is when we go
in with a catheter we enter either
through the wrist or through the groin
we wire the wire goes up through the
vessels into the heart we can inject dye
into the heart and when this happens we
do fluoroscopy to look at that dye going
through the heart and we're looking for
narrowing in the vessels that go around
the heart that feed the muscle if we
notice an area of narrowing we can then
go in with a balloon and a stent as the
bottom diagram shows we go in where that
clip that plaque buildup is we inflate
the balloon push that plaque up against
the vessel deploy the stent and put it
in place we deflate the balloon pull it
out and the stem
stays in place keeping that vessel open
and this is a great thing it renews
blood flow to the heart a lot of people
feel a lot more energy afterwards their
breathing gets better and their pain
goes away that they're experiencing
other procedures would be open-heart
surgery are also known as bypass surgery
some people call it a cabbage CABG which
is coronary artery bypass grafting when
we cannot go in and open up the vessels
with stents due to the number of stents
or blockages that are in the heart or
due to certain anatomy of the heart
muscle
we can do bypass surgery that's when we
take vessels out of the legs or the arms
we sew them onto the aorta and then onto
the vessel past the blockage or
narrowing this allows blood flow to go
from the aorta to the heart muscle we
can also use a blood vessel that's
inside the chest wall to do this also we
also can do valve replacement and
repairs at the same time when we're
doing open-heart surgery or bypass
surgery this is when we'll go inside the
heart and put in a new valve or put a
ring around the valve to help it open
and close properly
there's also called a tavern a Tavor is
when we go either through a vessel a
large vessel through the the shoulder
area or through the groin with something
that's similar to a stent but we go into
the valve and we deploy it in the valve
and you get a new valve that way we also
have pacemakers and defibrillators
defibrillators this is a device that we
insert underneath the skin typically the
left side of the chest since the
majority of people are right-handed and
we put wires up and through the vessel
and into the heart and those wires will
give a small electrical impulse to the
higher
to tell it when to beat a pacemaker
device is a little bit bigger presently
than a half-dollar
there are also much smaller ones that
are being used that are about the size
of a large multivitamin and that one is
inserted right into the heart
defibrillators are a little bit bigger
than a pacemaker they also have the
capacity of pacing the heart but they
can also defibrillate the heart in the
event you go into an irregular rhythm
that could stop the heart beating and
kill you last up we have the no blasians
so if you have irregular heart beats
such as a fib or regular SVT or anything
like that we can go in with catheters
into the heart and burn small little
areas to block that electrical pathway
that's causing the irregular heartbeats
and put you back into a normal sinus
rhythm this is very effective with a lot
of people who cannot be country their
rhythms cannot be controlled with
medications or things like that next up
is medications that are common with
cardiac patients we often call them the
fabulous five
that is your ACE inhibitor or ARB your
beta blockers aspirin blood thinners and
statins these are all designed in order
to help the heart it can reduce stress
on the heart by making it not work as
hard it can protect against plaque
buildup in the vessels in the heart it
can also protect against blood clots and
make blood flow easier through the
coronary arteries so ACE inhibitors
examples are at least in Aprill
enalapril any generic name that ends in
PR I L will indicate that you are an ACE
inhibitor the action of this drug is to
lower blood pressure by lowering blood
pressure the heart does not have to work
as hard to get the blood out of the
heart because the pressure is not as
great in the vessel
this allows the heart some time to
recover from a recent heart attack or
heart failure because it's not having to
work as hard remember any time you're on
a medication that lowers blood pressure
you might notice the side-effects of
dizziness lightheadedness things like
that so once you are started on these
drugs or anytime they're increase we
always try to remember to remind you to
rise slowly so if you're laying in bed
we want you to sit on the side of the
bed and pause there for several seconds
stand up pause for several seconds make
sure you're not dizzy or lightheaded as
you adjust to these new medications last
thing he wants you to do is jump out of
bed and land on your nose because you
got dizzy ace inhibitors also have a
side effect with several people that's a
dry persistent Cod this does bother some
people and other people they don't even
notice it if you are having issues with
this dry cough please talk to your
physician and they can switch you to the
other class of drug in this area that's
called an ARB such as little Sartain but
but make sure anytime that you're having
side effects that you definitely follow
up with your physician and not just stop
the medication beta-blockers examples of
these are metoprolol Vetal all and
atenolol if you look at the generic name
they all in l-o-l these drugs are beta
blockers what they do is they control
they do among two multi-purpose drug
what it does it can control and slow
down the heart rate and it also
decreases blood pressure by dilating the
vessels really important to know why
this one does two different things and
what's the purpose behind him slowing
down the heart rate is very important
because at the time of a heart attack
recent heart failure things like that
the heart muscle is not getting its
nutrition that it means nobody can slow
down that heart rate a little bit it
allows the blood to stay in those
vessels around the heart in that heart
muscle feeding that heart most
giving its it nutrients giving its
oxygen also decreasing the blood
pressure makes the heart not have to
work as hard so these are the two
reasons this is a great drug side
effects once again decreasing blood
pressure can cause lightheadedness
dizziness but can also cause a little
bit of sluggish or fatigue because we
are reducing the heart rate and then if
you are one that has a history of asthma
you might notice a little bit more
shortness of breath with this drug if
you're experiencing that side effect
please communicate with your physician
so they can come up with a plan for you
you might also notice your hands and
your feet are a little bit more cold on
this drug blood thinners that will be
aspirin and your anticoagulants and anti
platelets the purpose of these drugs is
to decrease the ability of your body to
make blood clots it is very important
once we put a foreign item in your body
such as a stent or a bowel that blood
does not clot around it your body will
see this as something as foreign the
blood will go there they'll try to get
rid of it
so we do not want this to happen because
the stent and the valves we just put in
your heart we want them to function
properly we want them to stay open we
want the blood to be able to flow
through also it is to help prevent
confirmation and people who have afib or
atrial fibrillation if you remember
right that's when I told you the top
part of the heart kind of Quivers and
beat irregularly and the bottom part
beats steady and normal when this
happens blood can kind of pool in that
top part of the heart possibly causing a
clot to form in that area and we do not
want this to happen that's why we put
you on these drugs these drugs can also
prevent heart attacks and strokes and
then let's discuss the side effects of
bleeding is the big one if we put you on
something that doesn't causes your body
not to clot as well you have increased
risk for bleeding um so you might see a
little bit more blood in your stool you
might have some in your urine nosebleeds
are huge here especially in
winter or allergy season when you're
blowing your nose a whole lot more so
make sure you are doing gentle nose
blowing so that you're not popping those
blood vessels in your nose and causing
nosebleeds
bleeding gums can also be an issue here
so make sure you're switching to a saw
tooth brush and gently brushing around
those gum lines be prepared for cuts and
scrapes they may bleed a little bit
longer you might have to hold pressure a
little bit longer on those and anytime
you have any trauma to the head or body
please follow up with it this and
position immediately it is very
important that you get checked out to
make sure that you do not have a bleed
going on somewhere so what are these
different anticoagulants so we've got
the aspirin and then the other anti
platelets are going to be your bRILINTA
your plavix your at the end these three
drugs are prescribed after the placement
of a stent you may be put on one of them
and then switch to a different one
because the side-effects or other
reasons the side effect for bRILINTA is
shortness of breath this is one that a
lot of people notice some people notice
immediately within a few hours of taking
other people do not notice for a day or
two and some people do not notice at all
a way to combat the shortness of breath
that comes with real intent is to take
some caffeine approximately 45 minutes
before you take your bright linty the
caffeine will counteract that shortness
of breath that you may feel if caffeine
does not work or if this is worsening or
getting intolerable shortness of breath
please follow up with your physician and
they will switch you to either the
plavix or the affiant in this case next
up is the anticoagulants that would be
your warfarin your Pradaxa your Eliquis
these drugs are all designed to prevent
blood clots and are often prescribed and
people have a history of blood clots
warfarin is the oldest of these drugs it
is the least expensive warfarin does
require regular blood draws to make sure
that the levels are appropriate in your
blood in order to prevent blood clots so
some people do find that one a little
bit limiting because they have to go to
the doctor frequently for blood draws
they also need to watch what they're
eating so you need to not eat the leafy
green vegetables you need to watch the
cranberry and cranberry juice we educate
people that it is alright to eat these
things but you do not want to eat all
these things that all sudden decide
you're stopping them because that would
change the level of coumadin or warfarin
in your system or we do not want you to
decide all this sudden that you're going
to become this really healthy eater and
you're only going to eat spinach and
lettuce and different things like that
because that will affect your levels so
anytime that you're going to make it
major changing the diet or you're going
to be doing a medication change such as
being put on an antibiotic please follow
up with a person who follows you for
warfarin and make sure that your levels
stay consistent while you're doing these
changes with Pradaxa and Eliquis there
is no need for blood draw so that is
definitely nice with those drugs they
are more expensive because they are
newer and sometimes insurance companies
do not cover them so please follow up
with your physician as to which one will
work best for you in this event
calcium channel blockers that would be
your and load of peeing your cart ISM
and your pro cardia these drug help
control blood pressure so once again
anything that control blood pressure can
cause a little bit of dizziness
lightheadedness things like that so be
cautious when you change positions these
drugs also help maintain normal rhythms
by decreasing irritability in the heart
other side effects that some people have
experience with these drugs is swelling
constipation and headache
if you were expel experiencing any of
these especially the swelling and weight
gain due to the swelling in the ankles
and legs please follow up with your
physician and make sure it is the side
effect of this medication and not
something else going on our cholesterol
medications they we primarily talk about
statins those would be your at arrests
at your simvastatin and drugs along
those lines that and an ST atin these
drugs are designed to help reduce the
cholesterol going throughout your body
in your blood system they decrease the
cholesterol and fat or try goes our
triglyceride levels in your blood by
interfering with absorption in the
intestines by stabilizing the existing
plaque and that's the huge part that a
lot of people forget about because a lot
of people who are diagnosed with recent
heart disease will say well my
cholesterol has been fine I've been
checking it for the last 10 15 years and
it's always been normal yes it's been
normal because you don't have excess
cholesterol floating through your blood
system but we know because we went in
with a heart catheterization that you do
have plaque in those vessels and they
may not be stable and they break off
float downstream and cause the heart
attack so these drug can stabilize that
existing plaque there and prevent it
from causing another heart attack the
side effects of these drugs are often
muscle and joint pain and that I hear
most frequently when people are first
started on it later I hear more about a
little bit of heartburn insomnia
difficulty sleeping things like that
this drug was originally designed to be
administered at night time so that if
you're experiencing side effects
hopefully did occur while you're
sleeping the thing with the heartburn
and difficulty sleeping kind of prevents
some of that so if you take the talk to
your physician take the drug with food
at supper time you should prevent some
of those other side effects also
other common medications that you might
be on our diuretics nitrates and
antiarrhythmics diuretics our design for
fluid management that would be your
lasix boom it's bumex spare laughter
flown hydrochlorothiazide these are
medications that will make you pee so
you need to remember that when you do
take plan it accordingly you don't want
to take it at nighttime this is a drug
that you'll take in the morning if
you're on a big road trip
time your drugs so that the you're not
making a lot of stops in the bathroom
things like that nitrates is the next
one they're short acting and long acting
the long-acting one is the M der and I
so swore by these helped to prevent or
stop angina or otherwise known as chest
pain the short acting ones such as
sublingual nitro or spray nitro
something that is for sudden pain versus
long-term or continuous pain
antiarrhythmics are to treat atrial
fibrillation and other irregular
heartbeats
that would be your amiodarone mult tach
sotalol and several other drugs there
are side effects with all these drugs
and if you are on them please follow up
with your physician to know what to
watch out for some medication concerns a
lot of people wonder will I ever get off
these medications I went into the
hospital on just a multivitamin and I
got this long list and I'm overwhelmed
you will get off the some of them or
some of them ad PE decreased if you're
in for a new stent or valve and you have
no history of blood clots you will
eventually get off your anti platelet
that drug you will be on for 365 days
some people are on it longer that have a
longer cardiac history we keep them on
for much longer than that but typically
it is for one calendar year take them as
prescribed if you need to adjust them
follow up with your physician that is a
huge thing
beep talk with your physician let them
know about your side effects let them
educate you with the purpose of the drug
work with you with modifying how you're
taking it or things like that these are
very important especially initially
after the heart attack always carry a
list of your medications in your wallet
or purse make sure you have the full
name of the drug on there if it is
metoprolol make sure you write the excel
at the end because there's a difference
between the tocrawl and metoprolol excel
make sure you have the dose the
frequency and if it's a specific drug
that you always take it to a clock
versus once a day make sure you write
that timeframe on there because if you
end up getting hospitalized we want to
make sure that we're giving you your
medications as close to your home
schedule as possible symptoms of a heart
attack this is going to be different for
everyone it is not always like we see on
TV of someone clenching their left side
their left arm and just sweating and
looking pale and miserable it is not
always that way some people will just
feel pressure or fullness in the chest
some people will describe it as the
worst heartburn of their lives some
people will say they'll have jaw pain
and they went to the dentist and their
dentist is Sundering the ER and they
think their dentist is another case but
it could be just in the center of your
back it could be radiating down one arm
both arms it's not going to be the same
for everyone just be aware of that
that it can just you can appear
differently in everyone you might have
numbness pain tingling nausea vomiting
fatigue shortness of breath if these are
very brief mild or big it's alright to
call your provider and let them know
what's going on if it's sudden intense
lasting or otherwise concerning that if
something in your head goes ooh I wonder
what this is definitely call 9-1-1 get
in it is so important to get medical
attention immediately especially if this
is a heart attack because time is muscle
we have 90 minutes to get in there to
open up a vessel before there's going to
be permanent damage
heart muscle so it is so important that
you are in tune with what's going on and
gets checked out
we would rather see you a hundred times
in the ER then never see you because you
have the big one and chose not to come
in
symptoms of worsening heart failure the
big one is fluid retention you're going
to see that in different ways depending
upon where that fluid retention is
you're going to feel swelling in the
feet legs or abdomen the pants are gonna
fit quite right the shoes are going to
be tight you might notice an increased
shortness of breath with activity or
when laying down in bed you might notice
that you are now sleeping with three
pillows instead of one pillow this is an
indication that you might have fluid
retention you have increased cough with
bringing stuff up you're gaining weight
the rule of thumb is if you gain more
than three pounds in 24 hours or five
days and five days you get in to be seen
by a physician think about what three
pounds would look like in 24 hours how
much food did you have to eat yesterday
in order to be three pounds heavier
today that is a lot a lot of food so it
is probably fluid retention you might
notice some chest pain worsening angina
palpitations weakness fatigue you can no
longer walk down to the mailbox this is
a huge one a lot of people say I used to
go get them now no issue and now without
even thinking about it they'll walk down
to the mailbox and they'll be checking
the mail before they head back up the
driveway to the house because they
realized they can't make that distance
and so they're naturally just taking a
break without really thinking about it
if you're someone like that who used to
be able to walk to the mailbox and back
and even think twice about it
something's going on please see your
physician and then last up is other
cardiovascular problems we got
peripheral artery disease also known as
PA D and stroke once you have been
diagnosed with coronary artery disease
that may mean you may have disease
throughout all vessels throughout your
body doctors are now going to be
checking Sarki
in your legs more often they're going to
be talking to you about pain when
walking checking your feet asking you if
you have wounds that are not healing
these are all signs that you have
peripheral artery disease or blockages
and vessels that are in your legs or
other parts of your body claudication is
a huge one you might notice pain in your
calves when walking which goes away when
sitting this pain is different than when
we were younger and we get the lactic
acid build up from running or playing
sports and we'd have that ache that
would last much longer in our legs
you may notice poor circulation in legs
and feet you may notice a little bit
more puffiness you may notice your feet
are a little bit more blue you may
notice a wound that doesn't heal quite
as fast or discoloration of the legs
these are all things that are important
to get checked out last up is the stroke
stroke is another medical emergency this
is something that you should be calling
999 fast FAS T we're looking at facial
droop if you're noticing someone one
side of the face not quite fully moving
when talking or their eyes a little bit
troupe here this appearance is very
similar to when someone has dental work
and they have numbing on one side of
their face if their face just does not
move quite like the other side next one
is arm drip if you have someone put both
arms out in front of them and the key
here is they need to close their eyes
when they do this if they keep their
eyes open and they're having a stroke
most people can still compensate and
keep their arms even but if you have
them close their eyes when both arms are
straight out in front of them you will
notice during a stroke one arm will
drift down and the other one will stay
stable next up is speech this can look
differently in in various strokes
someone may may be struggling for their
words they may rearrange their words in
sentences
they may slur their speech they may be
on incomprehensible next one is time
time is huge here we have three hours
from the onset of symptoms to get in and
fix a stroke before there's permanent
damage and three hours sounds like a lot
of time but in reality it's not
you've got getting them to the ER having
a stroke call overhead and getting the
on-call neurologist there
it requires running tests
it requires lowering blood pressure a
lot of people have stroke their blood
pressure goes way up high and we cannot
treat a stroke victim until their blood
pressure has been lowered to a
manageable level because the risks are
too high to treat them if their blood
pressures too high so it's really
important that we get them to the
hospital ASAP call 911
get the ambulance crew there because
they can communicate with the ER and
with that communication we can get the
neurologist on call in the ER before the
person shows up we can get the
telecommunication there of outside
agencies there also if need be so it is
very important that you think of fast
and follow fast thank you for listening
to this video if you ever have any
questions or wrote down notes throughout
the video and you want them answered
please reach out to us and contact us at
three oh seven six three three seven
zero six six we are available to answer
any of your questions thank you again